I'd like to hang ear so you're signed in to go to
I don't know what it is. Okay, so we're at the bottom
of פל"ב Palan Bet and we're going to pick up where Rabbi
Lumzer left off yesterday. The משנה Mishnah was about כל האומנין שומרי
שכר הן. Kol ha-umanin shomrei sachar hen.
Any craftsman who has something in his house and he is working
on it, you gave me the example Rabbi Lumzer gave, you give
me wood and I'm going to build you a box,
becomes a שומר שכר. shomer sachar. A שומר שכר shomer sachar is
חייב chayav on גניבה ואבדה. geneivah va-aveidah. So that means someone who
is כאילו ke'ilu being paid for their work of guarding an object
is liable if the thing is lost or stolen, to exclude things
that are damaged accidentally, אנוסין, anusin, he is not liable to pay.
So
the גמרא Gemara comes and it has a question that it seems
like our משנה Mishnah contradicts another משנה. Mishnah. It says
תנן התם. tenan hatam. According to some early ראשונים Rishonim and even
there's a גאונית Geonic תשובה tshuvah that says this, תנן התם tenan
hatam is supposed to mean that it says in a different מסכת
Masechet entirely, a different משנה. Mishnah. And if it's just a משנה
Mishnah in the same מסכת, Masechet, it should say והתנן, ve-ha-tenan, it
should say in our משנה. Mishnah.
The problem with this is that even early on this was never
true, and the printings and manuscripts of the בבלי Bavli already never
had תנן התם tenan hatam that was so consistent that תנן התם
tenan hatam is a different מסכת, Masechet,
which is an interesting question about how probably before they went into
manuscript and before they went into printing, the technical terms that introduce
ברייתות braitot were consistent or inconsistent by the גרסנים. garsanim. But that's
just a different question entirely. So תנן התם: tenan hatam: אמר לו
שואל שלח לי ביד בני ביד עבדי ביד שלוחי או ביד בנך
ביד עבדך ביד שלוחך ומתה חייב וכן בשעה שמחזירה. Amar lo shoel
shelach li beyad beni beyad avdi beyad shluchi o beyad bincha beyad
avdecha beyad shluchacha umetah chayav vechen beshaah shemachzirah. This is a משנה
Mishnah in צ"ח ע"ב. Tzadik-Chet amud bet. We're talking about a case
of borrowing. So let's read the whole משנה: Mishnah: צ"ח ע"ב, Tzadik-Chet
amud bet, השואל את הפרה ושלחה לו ביד בנו ביד עבדו ביד
שלוחו או ביד בנו ביד עבדו ביד שלוחו של שואל ומתה פטור.
Hashoel et haparah veshalacha lo beyad beno beyad avdo beyad shlucho o
beyad beno beyad avdo beyad shlucho shel shoel umetah patur.
So if I am going to Michael and I'm saying Michael can
I borrow your cow, and Michael sends it to me by way
of his son or his slave or some other agent, or he
sends it in my son or my slave or my agent, and
it dies before it gets to me, then I am פטור patur
from paying Michael for the cow. אמר לו השואל שלח לי ביד
בני ביד עבדי ביד שלוחי או ביד בנך ביד עבדך ביד שלוחך,
Amar lo hashoel shelach li beyad beni beyad avdi beyad shluchi o
beyad bincha beyad avdecha beyad shluchacha,
if I say to Michael, Michael can you do this in this
specific way, can you send it to me in this specific way,
או שאמר לו המשאיל, o she-amar lo hamashil, or if Michael says
to me, Avi I'm sending you the cow, הריני משלח לך ביד
בני ביד עבדי ביד שלוחי או ביד בנך ביד עבדך ביד שלוחך,
hareini meshale'ach lacha beyad beni beyad avdi beyad shluchi o beyad bincha
beyad avdecha beyad shluchacha, I'm going to send it to you this
way, ואמר לו שואל שלח, ve-amar lo shoel shelach,
and I say great that's fine, ומתה חייב, umetah chayav,
then I'm חייב chayav to pay Michael because it essentially went into
my hands the moment that we agree about how we're going to
send it to me. וכן בשעה שמחזירה. Vechen beshaah shemachzirah. And then
we have to reverse the entire thing for when I'm returning the
thing. So רש"י Rashi explains that on צ"ח ע"ב Tzadik-Chet amud bet
and he also explains it here, but I'm going to read it
out of צ"ח ע"ב: Tzadik-Chet amud bet: וכן בשעה שמחזירה, vechen beshaah
shemachzirah, אם שלח השואל ביד בנו ביד עבדו או שלוחו או ביד
עבדו וביד שלוחו של משאיל, im shalach hashoel beyad beno beyad avdo
o shlucho o beyad avdo uveyad shlucho shel mashil, if I'm sending
Michael back the cow in my son's or my slave's or my
agent's hands or I send it by his slave or his son
or his agent, לא
יצא מרשותו של שואל, lo yatza mershuto shel shoel, it hasn't gone
out of my רשות, reshut, my domain, של שואל, shel shoel, עד
שתבא ליד המשאיל, ad shetavo leyad hamashil, until it gets back to
Michael. And if it died, oh we had agreed beforehand. Say ah
no this is we hadn't agreed beforehand. ואם מתה בדרך חייב אמר
לו המשאיל שלח לי או שאמר לו השואל הריני משלח ואמר לו
המשאיל
שלח ושלחה ומתה פטור. Ve'im metah baderech chayav amar lo hamashil shelach
li o she-amar lo hashoel hareini meshale'ach va-amar lo hamashil shelach veshalacha
umetah patur. If we did agree beforehand that we were going to
do it this way, once it leaves, once it goes into the
hands of the שליח shaliach or the עבד eved or the בן,
ben, once it goes into the hands of the person who's going
to return it back to Michael and we know that it's happening
this way, I'm פטור, patur, it's gone out of my רשות. reshut.
So what's the problem here? That there seems to be some knowledge
that between the two people. It's like we have the same issue
of I have somebody else's property and I'm taking care of it
and so I'm supposed to be liable for damages up to a
certain point. And so here we say
that there is more חיוב, chiyuv, it's until it gets back until
the hands of the משאיל, mashil, until it gets back to the
owner's property, then I'm still חייב. chayav. And in our case of
the שומר שכר shomer sachar of the אומן uman who's considered a
שומר שכר, shomer sachar, I'm פטור patur from most things once I
say hi it's done, come take it and give me the money
you owe me. So that's a contradiction. אמר אפרים בר פפא אמר
רב חסדא לא שנו אלא שמחזירה בתוך ימי שאלתה אבל לאחר ימי
שאלתה פטור. Amar Efrayim bar Pappa amar Rav Chisda lo shanu ela
shemachzirah betoch yemei she'elatah aval le'achar yemei she'elatah patur. Okay,
we make an אוקימתא. okimta. We say no, that משנה Mishnah is
about a specific case. If it's בתוך ימי שאלתה betoch yemei she'elatah
within the days of the borrowing period, Michael thought I was going
to have it until the end of a month. And it's the
15th of the month. Actually, it's the 16th of the month.
And I'm bringing it back already. Okay, then I have more חיוב
chiyuv up until it gets back into the רשות reshut of the
משאיל mash'il until it gets back to Michael's hands.
But if it's after, it's already the first and it's the day
for me to bring it back. Everybody knows I'm bringing it back.
It doesn't matter how I'm sending it. Then I'm פטור patur and
everyone's happy and there's no more contradiction. מיתיבי רב נחמן בר פפא
וכולן שאמרו טול שלך והבא מעות שומר חינם הגמרתי שומר שכר. Metivei
Rav Nachman bar Pappa vechullan she'amru tol shelach vehavei ma'ot shomer chinam
hagamarti shomer sachar. Wait,
why is that the case? There's a difference between our two cases.
We said it's טול שלך והבא מעות. tol shelach vehavei ma'ot.
Over here it's not just that I'm done. It's that I said
a specific thing. I said, take your thing and then take your
thing that I've finished and then pay me. But just if I
told you I'm done, that's a different case. הגמרתיו שומר שכר. Hagamartiv
shomer sachar. לא, Lo, says the גמרא. Gemara.
No, you can't learn from טול שלך והבא מעות tol shelach vehavei
ma'ot
that just סתם stam saying I'm done means I'm still a שומר
שכר shomer sachar on your objects. הא הבא מעות וטול שלך שומר
שכר. Ha havei ma'ot vetol shelach shomer sachar.
No, if I reverse the order of my statement and I said,
give me my money and then you can have your thing back,
that's a שומר שכר. shomer sachar. You're getting paid. Yeah.
Like we saw in the last סוגיא. sugya. אבל גמרתי מאי
שומר חינם. Aval gamarti mai shomer chinam. No, גמרתי gamarti is the
same as טול שלך והבא מעות. tol shelach vehavei ma'ot. אי
הכי אדתני וכולן שאמרו טול שלך. Ei hachi adtane vechullan she'amru tol
shelach. We're at דף פא עמוד א daf pei alef amud alef
by the way. אי הכי אדתני
וכולן שאמרו טול שלך והבא מעות שומר חינם נשמעינן גמרתי וכל שכן
טול שלך. Ei hachi adtane vechullan she'amru tol shelach vehavei ma'ot shomer
chinam nashmi'inan gamarti vechol sheken tol shelach. The גמרא Gemara then asks
if it's true that גמרתי, gamarti, that telling you I'm done, is
the same as saying, take your thing that I finished and then
give me my money when you have a chance, then why does
the משנה Mishnah say the more complicated one? Why does it say
טול שלך והבא מעות? tol shelach vehavei ma'ot? Now the גמרא's Gemara
going to give one answer. There's a simple answer. The answer is
that the משנה Mishnah doesn't actually care what it says. The תוספתא
Tosefta here, the parallel תוספתא Tosefta says, it doesn't say טול שלך
והבא מעות, tol shelach vehavei ma'ot, it just says טול שלך. tol
shelach. And it also says גמרתי. gamarti. In the תוספתא, Tosefta, in
this case, it doesn't actually matter the order of what I say
or what precisely I say. It's precisely this point. If I say
I'm done in some way, take your thing, then we're good. I'm
no longer a שומר שכר, shomer sachar, I'm just a שומר חינם.
shomer chinam. And in fact, in the משנה Mishnah here, in other
גרסאות girsa'ot of the משנה, Mishnah, in the manuscripts of the משנה,
Mishnah, in the manuscripts of the ירושלמי, Yerushalmi, even in manuscripts of
the רי"ף, Rif,
we just saw that the order mattered. The order is reversed in
our משנה. Mishnah.
What happened probably just על פי מחקר al pi machkar is that
in chapter five in the משנה, Mishnah, it says הבא לי מעות
וטול שלך. havei li ma'ot vetol shelach. And there, when it's talking
about ריבית, ribbit, when it's talking about I've given you some of
the money for a thing and I say, give me the rest
of the money, the rest of the money, and take your stuff,
the order mattered there that you did something wrong.
We took that full statement from פרק ה Perek Hei and put
it in משנה ו, Mishnah Vav, probably by accident. And then either
because the order doesn't really matter here and in the transmission of
the משנה Mishnah it got mixed up, or in בבל Bavel where
we're going to make this דיוק diyuk where we're going where, sorry,
the order matters. Or because the order might matter a little bit
and it's a little confusing in our case to say הבא לי
מעות וטול שלך havei li ma'ot vetol shelach with regard to the
אומן uman who says I'm done with your box. We switched the
order so it says טול שלך tol shelach first. And then we
made the דיוק diyuk in בבל. Bavel. In any event, why it
happens, what happens is, the גמרא Gemara makes the דיוק. diyuk. And
the
גמרא Gemara says וכל שכן טול שלך. vechol sheken tol shelach. טול
שלך אצטריכא ליה. Tol shelach itztericha lei. No, we need to say
it this way. טול שלך והבא לי מעות Tol shelach vehavei li
ma'ot is really
important. סלקא דעתך אמינא Salka daitach amina I might have thought otherwise,
שומר חינם נמי לא הוי shomer chinam nami lo havei that these
people aren't even a שומר חינם. shomer chinam. They don't even rise
to that level. They don't need to take a שבועה shavuah if
something happens.
קא משמע לן. Ka mashma lan. Thus the משנה Mishnah says טול
שלך והבא לי מעות tol shelach vehavei li ma'ot because that's the
thing that I need to
learn and I can't learn that from
גמרתי. gamarti. I have to say explicitly, take your thing and give
me money to know that saying take your box and give me
the what you owe me makes me a שומר חינם shomer chinam
and no longer a שומר שכר. shomer sachar.
איכא דאמרי, Ika de'amri, a bit different version of our סוגיא sugya
that we just learned. אמר רב נחמן בר פפא, Amar Rav Nachman
bar Pappa, אף אנן נמי תנינא, Af anan nami tanina, וכולן שאמרו
טול שלך והבא
מעות vechulan she'amru tol shelcha vehavei ma'ot שומר חינם. shomer chinam. מאי
לאו הוא הדין גמרתי? Mai lav hu hadin gamarti? לא, Lo, טול
שלך שאני. tol shelcha shani.
Okay, so we just saw the whole thing again. He says, oh,
we have a משנה mishna that works like that משנה. mishna. Anytime
it says, anytime an אומן uman says, take your thing and give
me the money you owe me is now a שומר חינם. shomer
chinam. Isn't that also the case by גמרתי? gamarti? לא, Lo, טול
שלך שאני. tol shelcha shani. No, טול שלך tol shelcha is a
slightly different case and we need to say that explicitly, and so
it is not so straightforward to say גמרתי. gamarti. But the הלכה
halacha ends up being that גמרתי gamarti is the same
just so we know that. So we're moving on. We have this
third part of the סוגיא sugya that טול את שלך tol et
shelcha makes explicit the ownership
quest, where גמרתי gamarti just leaves it unstated. Right.
That makes sense to you, right? That's, yeah. Okay. Now we have
a third section of the סוגיא. sugya. הונא מר בר אמימר, Huna
mar bar Amemar, who's an אמורא Amora who appears only in this
סוגיא. sugya.
Never heard of him.
בר אמימר קמי דרבינא רמי מתניתא אהדדי ומשני. Bar Amemar kammei deRavina
rami matnita ahadadei umashni. He did the same סוגיא. sugya. He took
our two משניות mishnayot and he threw them up against each other
and then he made a result.
תנן וכולן שאמרו טול שלך והבא מעות שומר חינם, Tnan vechulan she'amru
tol shelcha vehavei ma'ot shomer chinam, והוא הדין לגמרתי, vehu hadin legamarti,
he comments. This is where we get that it's הוא הדין לגמרתי.
hu hadin legamarti.
Our משנה mishna says all of the אומנים umanim who say take
your object and give me the money you owe me are no
longer שומר שכר, shomer sachar, they're שומר חינם. shomer chinam. והוא הדין
לגמרתי, Vehu hadin legamarti, he adds, it's also the case if we
simply said I am done with your object.
ורמינהו, Ureminhu, however, there's another
משנה. mishna. אמר לו שואל שלח די שלך ומיתה חייב וכן בשעת
שמחזירה. Amar lo sho'el shelach di shelcha umeta chayav vechein besha'at shemachzira.
There's a problem between the two משניות mishnayot that we saw. ומשני,
Umashni, אמר רב הונא בר פפא, Amar Rav Huna bar Pappa, he
brings the same idea. אמר רב חסדא, Amar Rav Chisda, לא שנו
אלא שהחזיר בתוך ימי שאלתה אבל אחר ימי שאלתה פטור. lo shanu
ela shehechezir betoch yemei she'elata aval achar yemei she'elata patur. Great, the
same answer. Shofit comments on this point sort of tongue in cheek
to himself.
Isn't it interesting that this very late אמורא Amora who might not
even be an אמורא, Amora, he's one of the students of an
אמורא, Amora, is doing the same thing that we see the סתם
תלמוד Stam Talmud do all the time, which is that he asks
a question and then he uses an אוקימתא okimta of an אמורא
Amora to answer his own question. Hmm, isn't that interesting?
The tongue in cheek part of it being it looks like he
actually is the סתם Stam to some degree. אמימר Amemar was after
רב אשי, Rav Ashi, so this would be then even a further
generation. Right, right, precisely. So now we have a new סוגיא. sugya.
איבעיא להו, Ibaya lehu, the rabbis raise the question. The main point
was the סתם Stam has a name. Here the סתם Stam has
a name, at least. פטור
משואל וחייב כשומר שכר או דילמא
שומר שכר נמי לא הוי. Patur misho'el vechayav keshomer sachar o dilma
shomer sachar nami lo havei. So we're going to ask about
the question of the borrower. Once he is no longer, once he
is פטור, patur, does that mean he is only פטור patur from
אונסים onsim
but he's still considered a
שומר שכר? shomer sachar? But he still has liability for theft and
loss?
Or is he not even a שומר שכר shomer sachar and he's
a שומר חינם shomer chinam and he doesn't have liability for anything
and he can take a שבועה shvuah on those things?
אמר אמימר מסתברא פטור משואל וחייב כשומר שכר. Amar Amemar mistabra patur
misho'el vechayav keshomer sachar. אמימר Amemar says, no, makes sense that it
would be one and not the other, that it would be
that he's still a שומר שכר. shomer sachar.
הואיל וקא נהני מיניה, Ho'il veka neheni minei, because he's still getting
benefit from it. If I'm a שואל sho'el and I'm returning your
donkey back to you, it's okay, I still get some benefit from
it, and so then the benefit that I'm
getting is the שכר, sachar, and so I'm still liable for while
returning it to you, I'm still liable for loss and theft.
This is the הנאה hana'ah that he got as by virtue of
having borrowed it,
seemingly at the moment that he's returning it he's still getting benefit
from it. Yeah, what's that? Then riding on it, walking it somewhere,
looking at the clouds? What's the הנאה? hana'ah? Looks like he has
a חמור, chamor, I'm not sure exactly what the הנאה hana'ah is.
That's a good question. תניא כוותיה דאמימר, Tanya kavatei deAmemar, but we
have to go on. Sorry. תניא כוותיה דאמימר, Tanya kavatei deAmemar, there's
a ברייתא baraita that says like him. It's an interesting ברייתא. baraita.
הלוקח כלי מבית האומן לשגרו לבית חמיו. Halokeach kli mibeit ha'uman leshagro
leveit chamiv.
Somebody goes to the craftsman's house and says, hey, I want to
buy a present for my father-in-law. I'm going to... can you send
them to him? If he likes them, I'll pay you for them.
ואמר לו אם מקבלין אותם ממני אני משלם לך דמיהם. Ve-amar lo
im mekabelin otam mimeni ani meshalem lecha dameihem. I'll pay you for
them. אם לאו אני נותן לך לפי טובת הנאה, Im lav ani
noten lecha lefi tovat hana'ah, and if not, I'll just pay the
small amount that I the quantified benefit I get from my father-in-law
liking me more.
הנאה שבהן. hana'ah she-ba-hen. ונעשו בהליכה חייב. Ve-ne'ensu be-halicha chayav. And if
they were damaged while they were going to the father-in-law's house, he
is liable for that damage כשואל. ke-sho'el. ובחזרה פטור
מפני שהוא כנושא שכר, U-vi-chazira patur mipnei she-hu ke-nosei sachar, says explicitly
this other source. That but if they're coming back from the father-in-law's
house, he didn't want them, he's just going to... he's just getting
the הנאה, hana'ah, the הנאה hana'ah that the father-in-law says, "Oh, you
wanted to give me a present," which apparently can be quantified as
money, I am only...
I am not liable for the damage to the object because I
am like a נושא שכר, nosei sachar, which is a... another term
for a שומר שכר, shomer sachar,
a paid bailee. And thus I am still liable in that case
for loss and theft. And that is the same as what אמימר
Amemar said מסברא. mi-sevara.
ההוא גברא דזבין חמרא לחבריה. Hahu gavra de-zavin chamra le-chavreih. So now
we have
another case, which is a similar one. A certain
guy sold, he gave, it's sold... he sold a donkey to his
friend. אמר ליה קא ממטינא ליה לדוכתא פלניא. Amar leih ka mamtina
leh le-duchta pelanya. אם מזדבן מזבנא ואי לא מהדרנא ליה ניהלך. Im
mizdaban mizabna ve-i la me-hadarna leh niyahach.
So he says, "Okay, take the donkey over to such-and-such a place
and sell it there. And if he can't sell it there, come
bring it back, I'll take it back from you."
אזל ולא אזדבן. Azal ve-lo izdaban. ובחזירא דקאתי איתניס. U-ve-chazira de-ka-ati itnis.
He was coming back, he went, he didn't manage to sell the
donkey, and he's coming back, and on the way back it gets
hurt. אתא
לקמיה דרב נחמן חייביה. Ata le-kamei de-Rav Nachman chayveih. They come before,
they come before רב נחמן, Rav Nachman, they ask what's the דין,
din, do I owe him money? I was coming back. Normally when
I'm coming back, I'm not חייב chayav for אונסין. onsin. I'm not
חייב chayav on damage to the object.
אתא לקמיה דרב נחמן חייביה, Ata le-kamei de-Rav Nachman chayveih, but he
makes him liable. איתיביה רבא לרב נחמן. Eitiveih Rava le-Rav Nachman. רבא
Rava says to רב נחמן, Rav Nachman, "How can you say that?"
ונעשו בהליכה חייב ובחזרה פטור. Ve-ne'ensu be-halicha chayav u-vi-chazira patur. If I'm
just borrowing something going out to the... going to the place I'm
חייב, chayav, but returning it, no. מפני שהוא כנושא שכר, Mipnei she-hu
ke-nosei sachar, we saw in the last ברייתא. Baraita. Because when I'm
returning the object to the בית אומן bet uman in the ברייתא
Baraita that we just saw, I am only a נושא שכר. nosei
sachar. I'm only a paid bailee and I'm not חייב chayav for
damage to the object. אמר ליה
חזרה דהאי הליכה היא. Amar leih chazara de-hai halicha hi. Not all
returnings are the same. This returning is the same as a going.
Why? מאי טעמא סברא הוא. Mai ta'ama sevara hu. Oh, it's total
common sense. דחזרה דהאי אילו אשכח לזבוני מי לא זבנה. De-chazara de-hai
ilu ashcach le-zivunei mi la zavna. When he was coming back from
trying to sell an animal, he meets somebody on the road that
wanted to buy the animal. Isn't he going to sell him that?
So has he really changed in his mind his own status from
someone who's going out to sell something? Oh, I'm done with selling
this, I'm just returning this to my friend. No. He's still trying
to sell the animal. So obviously he's still כשואל ke-sho'el here. So
just trying to understand, you know, catching up in my mind from
before. We say בחזרה משואלתה be-chazira mi-sho'altah you're פטור. patur. Like I
guess this is very different than what we do. Like, you know,
let's say you need to return it, like, you know, you rent
a car, right? And you do it for 30 days. You go
the 31st day you're charged extra fees.
Not like... I mean, like, wouldn't you think that if you're extending
the term, not only should you not be פטור, patur, you should
be even more חייב? chayav? So I agree on that. We're talking
not about generally am I חייב chayav for this. This specific point
is how am I returning it to you? There's something here that
is like when we've made a decision about how this object is
being returned back, it's in my son or your son or my
slave or your slave. When we've made that decision בתוך ימי שאלתה,
be-toch yemei she'altah, then anything that happens in the process of returning
the animal to you, I'm פטור patur from, because we've made that
agreement. It's like if you're mailing back something you bought
online. Right. If it gets lost in the mail there... If it's
damaged on the mail, it's not my fault. That's a great example.
That's a great example. Now, after I'm returning it back, but it's
after the day, it's after the time that I'm supposed to return
it. But we both know that it needs to come back, says
רש״י. Rashi. Once we both know it needs to come back, we
don't need to make an agreement about how it goes back because
it has to go back to you. It's yours. And so once
it needs to go back to you, it's כאילו ke-ilu already slightly
in your רשות. reshut. It's already less my רשות reshut because the
period of the lease is over.
We do... it is a little... you're right at the end of
the day that it is strange that once it's a lease, so
it's like if
a
lease... And that's the point at which we're making our discussion. When
you said also it doesn't matter whether you say נטול שלך tol
shelcha and והבא מעות vehavei maot or נטול שלך tol shelcha or
גמרתי, gamarti, all that is שומר חינם, shomer chinam, what did we
mean by
that? שומר חינם, shomer chinam, just to go back over
the למעשה, lema'aseh, I'm an אומן, uman, I built you a box,
I say נטול שלך והבא מעות, tol shelcha vehavei maot, I'm a
שומר חינם. shomer chinam. גמרתי, gamarti, I'm a שומר חינם. shomer chinam.
If it's just, if I say according to the גמרא, Gemara, הבא
לי מעות ונטול שלך, havei li maot vetol shelcha, I'm still שומר
שכר. shomer sachar. Why? Because I'm saying I'm holding this, I'm holding
this until you pay me, like we saw in the previous סוגיא
sugya yesterday. Because at the end of the day we had this
מימרא meimra that seemed to
say because he didn't,
we weren't really sure because
then the גמרא Gemara had two ways of going to it. The
two ways of going to it still come to the conclusion of,
it only went through one way about the switching the order, but
we do conclude that גמרתי gamarti and נטול שלך tol shelcha first
are both שומר חינם, shomer chinam, and when we talked about the
order, we conclude that הבא לי מעות ונטול שלך havei li maot
vetol shelcha is a שומר שכר עדיין. shomer sachar adayin. Okay, next
סוגיא, sugya, which is a new thing. Back to the משנה. mishna.
שמור לי ואשמור לך שומר שכר. shmor li ve'eshmor lach shomer sachar.
Guard for me and I'll guard for you, that's a שומר שכר.
shomer sachar. Now,
I think Rabbi Linzer when going over the משנה mishna said, oh,
שמור לי היום ואשמור לך מחר. shmor li hayom ve'eshmor lach machar.
This is not necessarily פשט pshat in the משנה. mishna. שמור לי
ואשמור לך shmor li ve'eshmor lach is you go over there you
guard my thing, I'll be over here I'll guard your thing right
now. And then if it's שומר שכר, shomer sachar, it doesn't make
sense because normally if the owner of the object is in the
hire of the בעלים, ba'alim, that's not a שומר שכר, shomer sachar,
and that's only
שומר חינם. shomer chinam. Now, חייב? chayav? The owner is being or
the yeah. But why should he be חינם, chinam, he's getting paid?
Because he's paying me.
If I'm going to do this, this is the crucial point in
a lot of the cases that come up in this סוגיא. sugya.
If
I can't come up with a good explanation, the example is actually
in the גמרא, Gemara, so we'll just move forward and hopefully it
should make sense as we go along. But
move
forward with whether they're חייב באונסין, chayav be'onsin, because you still conclude
פטור? patur? Right, here this is whether they're חייב chayav for גניבה
gneiva of the cases we're going to deal with. So just on
פשט pshat in the משנה, mishna, whether we're talking about at the
same time or tomorrow and today,
the גמרא Gemara asks: ואמאי, ve'amai,
why is it the case that שמור לי ואשמור לך shmor li
ve'eshmor lach is a שומר שכר, shomer sachar, שמירה בבעלים הוא? shmira
biv'alim hu? This is when the בעלים ba'alim of the object, the
owner of the object is in the hire of, is doing work
for the בעלי. ba'ali.
אמר
רב פפא, amar rav pappa, is there a רש"י Rashi on this
that explains it better than I can off the top of my
head?
No. דאמר
ליה שמור לי היום ואשמור לך למחר. de'amar lei shmor li hayom
ve'eshmor lach lemachar. He gives פשט pshat in the משנה mishna is
not that we're doing it at the same time and I am
working for you, and thus
you're not a שומר שכר. shomer sachar.
It's that I'll do it today and you'll do it tomorrow. So
at the moment that you're guarding my thing,
I am not in your hire, and thus you are a שומר
שכר shomer sachar and not a שומר חינם. shomer chinam.
Good. תנו רבנן. tanu rabanan. A ברייתא braita is, you know, so
it has to be at that time? So if I say, tomorrow
we engage in a transaction, okay, give me a glass of water
tomorrow, it doesn't make פטור, patur, it only has to be today?
It's the קולא kula of שומר חינם shomer chinam that it's a
שומר חינם shomer chinam when it's שמירה בבעלים shmira biv'alim is only
when it's at the moment that I'm doing שמירה, shmira,
or at the moment that you're doing שמירה shmira I am working
for you at that very moment, and that's going to be crucial
in the case that we're going to see in a minute. Right,
but not if I contract you at that moment to do something
tomorrow? Even if it's an hour from now, even if I don't
happen to be doing it at the moment. So this we're going
to see in a second.
So the ברייתא braita says: שמור לי ואשמור לך, השאילני ואשאילך, שמור
לי ואשאילך, השאילני ואשמור לך. shmor li ve'eshmor lach, hash'ileini ve'ash'ilecha, shmor
li ve'ash'ilecha, hash'ileini ve'eshmor lach. They mix the cases that the ruling
is the same whether it's I'll borrow from you or I'll lend
to you, I'll borrow from you and I'll guard for you, those
can all go together. כולן נעשו שומרי שכר זה לזה. kulan na'asu
shomrei sachar zeh lazeh. ואמאי? ve'amai? שמירה בבעלים הוא? shmira biv'alim hu?
אמר רב פפא, amar rav pappa, דאמר ליה שמור לי היום ואשמור
לך למחר. de'amar lei shmor li hayom ve'eshmor lach lemachar. We say
the same פשט pshat that it's not at the same time, lend
me this I'll lend you that, guard this for me I'll guard
this for you, it's do this for me today and I'll do
this for you tomorrow. So even though the השאילני? hash'ileini? Yes, we
say they're the same דין. din. It's not a שואל sho'el at
all and then שומר שכר, shomer sachar, they both get downgraded? They
both get upgraded to the higher level of פטור? patur? No, השאילני
ואשאילך, hash'ileini ve'ash'ilecha, if I'm a שואל sho'el I'm חייב באונסין. chayav
be'onsin. But if we say now
you're שומר שכר, shomer sachar, you're
חייב אמ... chayav am... So probably because the original Rav Papa is
only about the Mishnah and Rav Papa gets moved down to be
commenting, giving פשט Pshat in the Baraita, and really Rav Papa should
be taken to mean that you're right and Rav Papa means, okay,
he's a—he's a שואל, Shoel, a full שואל, Shoel, and it's not
שאילה בבעלים. Sheilah B'balim.
שאילה בבעלים Sheilah B'balim is treated sometimes the same as שמירה בבעלים.
Shmirah B'balim. Okay,
to the depth of the discussion we're having. שמור לי ואשמור לך
ולמחר, Shmor li ve'ashmor lach ulemachar, הנהו אלוי דכל יומא הוה אפי
לחד מנייהו. Hanhu aloi d'chol yoma hava api lechad minaihu. There was
once a group of perfume makers, every day one of them would
go out and do the baking.
And they would bake bread for everybody. ההוא יומא אמרו ליה לחד
מנייהו זיל אפי לן. Hahu yoma amru leh lechad minaihu zil api
lan. One day
they said to Stan, Stan you go do the baking today. אמר
להו נטרו לי גלימאי. Amar lehu natru li glimai.
Okay,
you guys guard my coat. אדאתא פשעו בה ואגנוב. Ada'ata pash'u bah
ve'agnuv.
Before he came back with the bread, his coat was
stolen. אתו לקמיה דרב פפא חייבינהו. Atu lekamei deRav Papa chayavinhu. And
he said oh, Rav Papa said you guys are liable for his
coat. He told you to guard his coat
and so
you're a שומר שכר. Shomer Sachar. אמרו ליה רבנן לרב פפא אמאי
פשיעה בבעלים היא? Amru leh rabbanan leRav Papa amai pshiah b'balim hi?
No, he was working for them. How's he a שומר שכר? Shomer
Sachar? He's a שומר חינם. Shomer Chinam.
איכסיף, Achsif, and he was ashamed because he knew that that was
the דין Din he agreed. ולסוף איגלאי מילתא דההיא שעתא שיכרא הוה
קא שתי. Ulesof iglai milta d'hahi sha'ata shichra hava ka shati. Turns
out that at that—not that he was drunk, I know that's what
it looks like—at the moment that it was stolen, he was not
baking it, he'd gone off, he was having a drink and so
he wasn't yet at that very moment in the employ of the
other perfume makers. And so it wasn't פשיעה בבעלים, Pshiah B'balim, it
was—and they were—they had the דין Din of שומר שכר Shomer Sachar
and they're liable for
theft. הניחא למאן דאמר פשיעה בבעלים פטור
משום הכי איכסיף. Hanicha leman d'amar pshiah b'balim patur mishum hachi achsif.
Well so it only—only makes sense, the whole story only makes sense
if we hold that פשיעה בבעלים, Pshiah B'balim, that if I was
guarding something for my friend while he was working for me, that's
a שומר חינם Shomer Chinam and I'm פטור. Patur. משום הכי, Mishum
hachi, that's the only reason he would be ashamed. משום הכי איכסיף.
Mishum hachi achsif. אלא למאן דאמר חייב אמאי איכסיף? Ela leman d'amar
chayav amai achsif? If we hold that I'm חייב Chayav even in
that case, why was he ashamed? אלא ההוא יומא לאו דידיה הוה.
Ela hahu yoma lav dideh hava. Oh, so that day wasn't really
his day to do—to do the baking. ואמרו ליה לדידיה זיל אפי
את ואמר להו בהאי אגרא דקא אפינא לכו נטרו גלימאי. Ve'amru leh
ledideh zil api at ve'amar lehu behai agra d'ka apeina lechu natru
glimai. And he says explicitly—it's the same case—explicitly he says:
My—the salary for doing this work today on the day that's not
normally my day (Stan normally cooks on Wednesdays and today it's Thursday)
and he says: Fine, I'll do—I'll do the work today, but you're
going to have to pay me for this by guarding my
coat. אדאתא אגנוב. Ada'ata agnuv. And again the same case: before he
came back it was—it was stolen. אתו לקמיה דרב פפא חייבינהו. Atu
lekamei deRav Papa chayavinhu. And he says the same ruling. אמרו ליה
רבנן לרב פפא הא שמירה בבעלים היא? Amru leh rabbanan leRav Papa
ha shmirah b'balim hi? איכסיף ולסוף איגלאי מילתא דההיא שעתא שיכרא הוה
קא שתי. Achsif ulesof iglai milta d'hahi sha'ata shichra hava ka shati.
So he should be—he should be חייב Chayav and here he was
not because it was in the—higher, because it was explicitly in the
higher, that's why Rav Papa came back, that it's שמירה בבעלים. Shmirah
B'balim. ולסוף איגלאי מילתא דההיא שעתא שיכרא הוה קא שתי. Ulesof iglai
milta d'hahi sha'ata shichra hava ka shati. And thus the same conclusion
that really Rav Papa—that really Rav Papa was right, Rav Papa was
right to say they are חייב Chayav because at the very moment
that the theft occurred he was not yet in the higher and
the explicit higher of the other perfume makers.
And so when it was stolen they were חייב Chayav as
שומרי שכר. Shomrei Sachar. And to say this is only the answer
according to one side. Yes, this second—this second version where he says
explicitly my payment for baking for you on Thursday
will be that you're going to guard my coat, only in that
case do we need to go—only in that case do we need
to go through it again. That's—we make that addition to the story
for Rav Papa to make sense according to למאן דאמר פשיעה בבעלים
חייב. leman d'amar pshiah b'balim chayav. He hadn't started the job. He
hadn't started the job. That was the point I was saying earlier,
that it's not just: you do this, do this. It's at the
very moment. If I'm guarding Michael's חמור Chamor and it gets stolen
at the very moment that Michael is also making me lunch and
we're paying each other for that, then I am פטור. Patur. But
wait, is this only if you ask me to make lunch? What
if I just decide and I'm doing this—very engagingly—just to get out
of anything, right? If I just decide, simple עורמה, Orma, okay, here,
you know, let me scratch your back for two seconds. I mean
like, you know, like... I say something you, you asked me to
make lunch and I'm sort of in your... I think the point
is... So here we're using the, we're using this to make the
point that it's at the very moment. But let's say the real,
the better example is that you are, is that
I am your,
sorry, who has to be who? I'm working for you. I'm your
contractor. I'm building your, I'm fixing your house. And it's going to
take me days. And I say, can you, can
you hold onto my, can you hold onto my computer for me?
Can you watch my dog for me while I'm working on your
house? You say sure, you're only ever a שומר חינם. shomer chinam.
Because it gets, you're not or, yeah, you're only ever a שומר
חינם, shomer chinam, so you're not חייב chayav for loss and for
loss and theft. Why? I could still be... wait, am I watching
the food the entire time or just for two minutes? No, I'm
watching, you're watching for the entire, you're watching for a day. From,
from Monday to Friday I'm working on your house. I'm working for
you. Can you move my car? You move it and, no, not
an accident. Well, also an accident, but it gets stolen. Gets stolen.
It's stolen, it's not really your fault. I mean, it is your
fault because you messed up, but it's not your fault, you're not
liable to pay me for it. It's so, it's like this is
the, this is the particular case that it's like, can you go
move my car?
And it's and at the very moment that you're moving my car,
it turns out I was on a lunch break and so I'm
not working for you at that, now this is a bad case
because it's קבלנות kablanut and so I'm doing it for you for
a period of time. But let's say, you're only in my hire,
I say I'm only in your hire while I'm working on the
house and when I'm on my hour-long lunch break from twelve to
one and I asked you sometime in the morning, hey, can you
move my car, it's opposite, it's alternate-side parking, and you go and
do
it and then between while you're doing it somebody breaks into the
car and steals the car away from you. Oh, okay then you're,
then you might be חייב, chayav, right?
So then you would be חייב chayav because I was on my
lunch break at that time. But so these are, those are the
borderline cases. The point is that when I am in your hire
and I ask you to guard something for me, you're not חייב
chayav for גנבה ואבידה. gneiva va'aveida. Unless you asked me, in other
words, like let's say like, you know, the I'm just asking about
a favor. If you're doing it as a favor I don't think
it would apply, but I don't know for sure. Let us move
on to the next section.
Okay, we have a different case about a short guy and a
tall guy. הנהו בי תרי דהוו קאזלי באורחא. haneihu bei terei dehavu
ka'azlei be'orcha. They were walking on the way. חד אריך וחד גוץ.
chad arich vechad gutz. One was tall and one was short. What
are the names of the people from Mice and Men? Oh, oh,
oh.
Okay, it doesn't matter.
Okay, so tall guy, there's, there's tall and shorty. So tall was
אריכא רכיב חמרא דהוה ליה סדינא. aricha rachiv chamara dehavu lei sadina.
So tall was riding on a donkey. I don't know why the
tall guy's riding on the donkey, he can take longer steps.
And he had a linen sheet that he was wearing, or he
had it on the donkey. גוצא מיכסי סרבלא וקאזלי בתריה. gutza michasei
sarbala veka'azlei batrei.
Shorty was wearing a woolen coat, which is very heavy, and he
was walking on his own two feet. כי מטו לנהרא שקליה לסרבלא
ואותביה אעילוי חמרא ושקליה
לסדיניה דההוא ואיכסי ביה. ki matu lenahara shaklei lesarbala ve'otvei eiluy chamara
veshaklei lesadinei dehu ve'ichasei bei. This actually gets to your question Michael
about you doing me a favor, כאילו. ke'ilu. But
it, it might answer it I believe. שקליה לסדיניה
דההוא ואיכסי ביה שקלו מיא לסדינא. shaklei lesadinei dehu ve'ichasei bei shaklu
maya lesadina. Okay, what happened? They get to the river and he's
like, I don't really want to wear this big woolen sheet near
the river any, near the river anymore. Takes off the woolen sheet,
puts it on the donkey. He says, okay, tall, can you, I'm
going to put this on the sheet, I'm going to put my
woolen coat on the donkey. He says, fine. I'm going to take
your סדינא. sadina. Your, סדינא sadina is a linen, is a woolen
sheet of some sort, not a woolen sheet, a linen thing you
wrap yourself in. Like a tunic? Yeah, it's a tunic.
Well, it's not a tunic, it's something,
it's not a
curtain if you're wrapping yourself. So he takes it, yeah. Go into
the water with that. Why would he do that? Right, and then
it walks away and then it washes away and I lose my,
I lose the guy's סדינא. sadina.
Okay.
At the very moment that I'm wearing his סדינא, sadina, he is
carrying my סרבל. sarbal. That's the important part is that he is
guarding my סרבל. sarbal. He's, he is in my hire while I
have borrowed this thing from him. We didn't ask him to, so
we're assuming in this case for the first version of the case
we're assuming that he asked him to. We're going to get to
that point in a moment.
אתו לקמיה דרבה. atu lekamei deRabba. They came to Rabba. חייביה. chayvei.
He said, oh, you're חייב chayav for the סדינא. sadina.
The water carried it away. You, שטפה מיא לסדינא. shatfa maya lesadina.
He lost, he lost the סדינא. sadina. אמרו ליה רבנן
לרבה אמאי שאלה בבעלים היא. amru lei rabanan leRabba amai sheila biba'alim
hi. What are you talking about? He was guarding, the one guy
was guarding the סרבל sarbal and the other one had the סדינא,
sadina, so how is he חייב chayav for אבידה? aveida? וסוף
היגא מילתא דבלא דעתיה שקליה, V’sof higei milta d’belo datei shaklei,
oh, he took it, he put it there without asking, so he
didn't know that he was a שומר shomer at the moment that
he was a שומר. shomer. Now, let's say I do know but
I don't say anything, is that considered that I agree? That is
a good question, I don't know. אותביה ההוא גברא דאוקמיה, Otvei hahu
gavra d’okmei,
oh, סייעיה
דאוקמיה. seiyayei d’okmei. He gave it to him without his knowledge. אותביה.
Otvei. Okay, right, you're right. ובלא דעתיה אותביה. U'vlo datei otvei. Oh,
and so because he was a
שומר שלא מדעת shomer she-lo mi-da'at that he was not, it was
not the בעלים, ba'alim, he was not in the hire of him,
and thus he the other guy was in fact חייב chayav as
רבא Rava said initially. So it seems like we're making the cases,
I mean we're, it seems like we're kind of making the cases
to justify the rabbis' rulings, you know what I mean? Is that
what it seems like to me? Do you get that impression? No,
actually, I get the opposite impression. That they're put here because they're
of interest. I think the second part, it's like if we want
to be very critical towards the text, I think we might say
that the וסוף היגא מילתא v’sof higei milta part makes it, that
that, it's like really the case was one way and the רבנן
rabanan said to the רבא Rava who was who was judging the
case, wait, that's wrong and he was ashamed and they changed and
they changed the ruling, אלא וסוף היגא מילתא ala v’sof higei milta
that he was right to begin with. That's a little too perfect,
that's a little precious. That's what I'm saying. I agree, I think
that might be the case, that might be true, but within the
context of these stories it's still they're still being used to teach
the point. So there was the premise of the וסוף היגא מילתא.
v’sof higei milta. No, even the וסוף היגא מילתא v’sof higei milta
also helps us to learn the rule because וסוף היגא מילתא בההוא
שעתא v’sof higei milta b’hahu sha’ata we learn the fact that if
it was a שומר שלא מדעת shomer she-lo mi-da'at he's not a
שומר. shomer. I don't want to say that explicitly because there's probably
a long discussion on שומר שלא מדעת, shomer she-lo mi-da'at,
so bracketing that and moving on to the next section. But
גוצה פריסתיה gutza paristei put his סרבלא sarbala on the חמרא chamra
without asking and took, that's וסוף היגא מילתא. v’sof higei milta. Right,
וסוף היגא v'sof higei he took the גולפא gulpa without asking. גולפא
gulpa without asking, I don't know, probably not. Why? לסוף היגא מילתא
דבלא דעתיה שקליה ובלא דעתיה. L'sof higei milta d'belo datei shaklei u'vlo
datei. Yeah, you're right, yeah, you're right, without asking either time, so
he's a שואל שלא מדעת sho’el she-lo mi-da'at and a שומר שלא
מדעת shomer she-lo mi-da'at and so he should be חייב. chayav. Good,
thank you. That helps with making sure I read it right. You
did read it right, I didn't read it right. Good. ההוא גברא
דאוגר ליה חמרא לחבריה, Hahu gavra d’oger lei chamra l’chavrei, new case,
a guy
hired a donkey to his friend. אמר ליה חזי, Amar lei chazi,
לא תיזיל באורחא דנהר פקוד, lo tizil b’orcha d’nahar pakod,
don't go that way, don't go by the נהר
פקוד nahar pakod דאיכא מיא, d’ika maya, because there's a lot of
water there and it'll hurt the donkey. וזיל באורחא דנרש, V’zil b’orcha
d’narash,
go the other way, go by the אורחא דנרש, orcha d’narash, go
by נרש narash road, דליכא
מיא, d’leika maya, there's no water there, everything will be okay. אזל
באורחא דנהר פקוד, Azal b’orcha d’nahar pakod, he ignored him, did you
want to know where these are? Those are real things? Okay, those
cities in Bavel. Of course they are. אזל באורחא דנהר פקוד, Azal
b’orcha d’nahar pakod, he went the wrong way, ומית חמרא, u'meis chamra,
and the donkey died. כי אתא אמר, Ki ata amar, when he
came before the רבא, Rava, אמר אין באורחא דנהר פקוד אזלי, Amar
ein b’orcha d’nahar pakod azli,
I did go that way, ומיהו ליכא מיא, u’mihu leika maya, there
wasn't any water there, I don't know what you're talking about says
the guy. I mean he went the wrong way, he should be
חייב, chayav, but there was no water there. אז חמרא ומית, Az
chamra u'meis, it died, it died. It died, and the donkey died,
that's the problem, it died in the water, the guy comes, there
wasn't any water by נהר פקוד. nahar pakod. The owner told me
not to go by נהר פקוד, nahar pakod, I got to נהר
פקוד nahar pakod and there wasn't any water there so I went
and the donkey died anyway. I did what he, I did what
he told me to do essentially, I didn't go in water,
he says.
So אמר ליה רבא מה לי לשקר, amar lei Rava mah li
l'shaker, why would he lie? אי בעי אמר ליה
באורחא דנרש אזלי. Ei ba'ei amar lei b'orcha d'narash azli. Here's a
מיגו. miggo. If he's telling me that I went by נהר פקוד
nahar pakod and there wasn't מיא, maya, I have to believe him
because he could have just told me I went by נרש narash
and it died not by water. So I have to believe him.
אביי Abaye says, no, you're wrong, completely wrong. Why? אמר ליה אביי
מה לי לשקר במקום עדים לא אמרינן. Amar lei Abaye mah li
l'shaker b'makom eidim lo amrinan. We don't make a מיגו miggo when
there's עדות. eidus. Now
who's the עדים? eidim? Everybody. It's an אנן סהדי, anan sahadei, which
is interesting to me that if everybody knows that you're lying, even
though you have a מיגו, miggo, you're still lying.
So if everybody knows, who's the everybody who knows? Everyone in those
places. So
everybody knows that נהר פקוד nahar pakod is filled with water. So
you're saying the guy was lying when he said... So everybody knows
the guy was lying. רבא Rava is like, I guess, I guess
if he tells me that there was no water by נהר פקוד...
nahar pakod... Oh, I see.
...that there was no traffic, there was no traffic in Times Square,
I didn't see a single person there, I didn't see a single
person there. He could have told me that he was at Herald
Square, but he told me he was at Times Square and there
was nobody there, I have to believe him. אביי Abaye is like,
what are you talking about?
Yeah, that's what he thought. That's the מיגו. Migo.
There was a רי"ף Rif here even with the, even with the
general opinion. Yeah, you're right. I forgot the רי"ף Rif says something
here then the, then the נימוקי יוסף, Nimukei Yosef, so that must
be what the רי"ף Rif says. I forgot what he says. Thank
you. Yeah. Okay, it is wonderfully ridiculous.
שמור Shemor now we're on to the next point. שמור לי ואמר
לו הנח לפני שומר
חנם. Shemor li ve'amar lo hanach lefanai shomer chinam. He says if
I say to Michael, can you keep this for me? And he
says put it down, that's a שומר חנם. shomer chinam. I accept
responsibility only
as שומר חנם. shomer chinam. אמר
רב הונא אמר לו
הנח לפניך אינו לא שומר חנם ולא שומר שכר. Amar Rav Huna
amar lo hanach lefanecha eino lo shomer chinam v'lo shomer
sachar. איבעיא להו הנח סתם מאי. Ibaiya lehu hanach stam mai. Okay,
so he says I'm going to put this down, put it down.
Michael says, I'm sitting next to Michael in the שוק, shuk, I
say Michael can you watch this, can you watch this for me?
And he says put it down in front of you.
Michael isn't accepting responsibility. I said put it down in front of
yourself. In front of myself. And you're like, that's saying I'm not
really accepting responsibility for that at all, not even as שומר חנם.
shomer chinam. That's the first point. אמר
רב הונא, Amar Rav Huna, לא שומר חנם ולא שומר שכר. lo
shomer chinam v'lo shomer sachar. איבעיא להו Ibaiya lehu but they ask
הנח סתם מאי? hanach stam mai? If I say Michael, can you
watch, can you watch this for me? And he says put it
down,
is that anything? What is that? Unclear. He's not saying just leave
it like no, and he's not saying yes. He's saying something and
it's unclear. He's saying put it in front of you is basically
saying the same thing as saying no, and he means he's basically
saying yes, put it down, we don't know. Yes.
תא שמע, Ta shma, שמור לי ואמר לו הנח לפני. shemor li
ve'amar lo hanach lefanai. So the משנה Mishnah says guard for I
ask Michael to guard it for me and he says put it
down in front of me,
שומר חנם. shomer chinam. הא סתם ולא כלום. Ha stam v'lo klum.
If he just says שמור, shemor, that's nothing, that's the same as,
or if he just says הנח hanach is the same as הנח
לפני. hanach lefanai. אדרבה מדאמר רב
הונא הנח לפניך הוא דאינו לא שומר חנם ולא שומר שכר. Adaraba
mide'amar Rav Huna hanach lefanecha hu de'eino lo shomer chinam v'lo shomer
sachar. No, we said רב הונא Rav Huna told us that הנח
לפניך, hanach lefanecha, put it down in front of you is rejecting
responsibility for it. הוא דאינו לא שומר חנם ולא שומר שכר. Hu
de'eino lo shomer chinam v'lo shomer sachar. הא סתם שומר חנם הוא,
Ha stam shomer chinam hu, it's just saying putting it down, okay
put it down, that's the same as הנח לפני. hanach lefanai. Makes
sense to me. אלא מהא ליכא למשמע מינה. Ella me'ha leka lemeshmane.
But we really can't learn, we can't learn anything. לימא כתנאי Leima
ketannai and maybe it goes like a מחלוקת תנאי. machloket tannai. אם
הכניס ברשות בעל החצר. Im hichnis bi'reshut ba'al hachatzer. If I'm moving
כלים kelim into the, into the חצר chatzer of somebody else
and they get damaged in
there,
I am חייב. chayav. חייב בנזקו. chayav binizko. דכי אמר ליה עול
ואנטר לך. Deki amar leh o'ol v'antar lach. The בעל החצר ba'al
hachatzer becomes חייב chayav for the כלים kelim that I'm putting in
his חצר. chatzer. רש"י Rashi explains he is
חייב. chayav. בעל... whose כלים kelim, are they?
Whose כלים, they're mine, I'm leaving them in the בעל החצר, ba'al
hachatzer, the בעל החצר ba'al hachatzer is a שומר חנם shomer chinam
and he's חייב. chayav. So you put your stuff in my backyard
with your permission according to... with permission. That becomes the issue of
what sort of permission am I giving you when I say okay.
How is permission conveyed? Exactly. And what do I say and what
does it mean? אם הכניס ברשות חייב. Im hichnis bi'reshut chayav. Then
I have some measure of responsibility, שומר חנם. shomer chinam. Right. רבי
אומר דכולם אינו חייב עד שיקבל עליו בעל הבית לשמור. Rabbi omer
de'kulam eino chayav ad she'yikabel alav ba'al habayit lishmor.
Only if you say yes, Avi, I will be in charge of
your stuff. Explicitly.
Explicitly. ממאי? Mimmai? דילמא עד כאן לא קאמרי רבנן התם אלא בחצר
דבת נטירה היא. Dilma ad kan la ka'amar rabanan hatam ella bechatzer
de'bat netirah hi. וכי קאמר ליה עול עול
דאנטר לך קאמר. V'chi ka'amar leh ayl ayl de'antar lach ka'amar. Oh,
maybe that, maybe there's a different case because in terms of a
חצר chatzer is a חצר chatzer is a place that is generally
guarded and so when Rabbi Dov told me, Avi, you can leave
your bike in my backyard, he's saying leave your bike in my
backyard, I will accept responsibility for guarding your bike because I'm putting
it there. אבל הכא שוקא לאו בר נטירה היא. Aval hacha shuka
lav bar netirah hi. If I'm just in the שוק shuk
and I'm next to Michael and Michael and Michael says סתם, stam,
put it down, הוא הנח ותיב נטר לך קאמר ליה. hu hanach
v'teiv natar lach ka'amar leh.
It would have to be that he's saying okay sit down put
it down and I will guard it for you. He has to
say it explicitly there. אי נמי Ee nami alternatively according to the
opinion of רבי Rebi how do we explain the opinion of רבי
Rebi in light of the two cases? לא קאמר רבי התם לגבי
החצר אלא בחצירו דלעלויי רשותא בעי למשקל מיניה Lo ka'amar Rebi hatam
legabei hachatzer ela bechatzeiro d'le'iluyei reshuta ba'ei lemishkal minei
even to go into Rabbi Dov's backyard I need permission. And so
for Rabbi Dov to say put it here is telling me come
in and only come in not saying that he will be guard
it for me. וכי יהיב ליה רשותא לעלויי תיב ונטר לך קאמר
ליה והכא הנח ואנא מנטרנא לך קאמר ליה. Vechi yahiv lei reshuta
le'iluyei tiv venatar lach ka'amar lei vehacha hanach ve'ana menatarna lach ka'amar
lei. Or it's like because and sorry it
is
it's the opposite. If he's giving permission to come into his house
and put it here he's giving me stop he's giving me implicit
permission that he's also going to guard it according to רבי Rebi
because if I am in the שוק shuk he says והכא הנח
ואנא מנטרנא לך קאמר ליה דאי סלקא דעתך הנח ותיב ונטר לך
קאמר ליה אטו טיבו רשותא בעי משקל מיניה? Vehacha hanach ve'ana menatarna
lach ka'amar lei de'ee salka daitach hanach vetiv venatar lach ka'amar lei
atu tivu reshuta ba'ei mishkal minei?
If I'm telling you and I'm in the שוק shuk okay put
it down since when do I need do you need to give
me permission in the שוק shuk to put something down? If you're
giving me permission to put something down הנח hanach
that means also and I will guard it for you because I
don't need your permission. So now to go back again and correct
my mistake
רבנן Rabbanan when they say over there
I need permission to go into your yard at all. And that's
when you give me permission to go in you're just giving me
permission to put it you're not accepting any responsibility. You need to
give me explicit or you need to give me explicit permission to
you need to make explicit that you're taking on guardianship in order
for there to be any
שמירה. shmira. Instead of just giving him permission to enter. Right which
you need.
So if I'm going to also assume responsibility for guarding I need
to make that explicit. Yeah. Here however
here watch my luggage yeah yeah yeah put it down and I'm
in the שוק shuk that means I'm assuming the שוק shuk I
already right. And
here I'm not getting this right. I'm sorry. והכא הנח ואנא מנטרנא
לך קאמר ליה Vehacha hanach ve'ana menatarna lach ka'amar lei אטו טיבו
רשותא בעי משקל מיניה atu tivu reshuta ba'ei mishkal minei שאין שמירה
כשל זו. she'ein shmira keshel zo.
Sorry
no the first case we're making they make the same case in
both places but for different reasons. In the one
place right the חצר דבת נטורי chatzer d'bat neturei the חצר chatzer
is somewhere that is generally guarded so saying I can put it
down here
is already even to come in and put it down is already
saying and I will guard it because I generally guard my חצר.
chatzer.
Sorry I did have it right the first time. The first way
was right. אבל הכא שוקא לאו בת נטורי היא הנח ואנא מנטרנא
לך קאמר ליה. Avel hacha shuka lav bat neturei hi hanach ve'ana
menatarna lach ka'amar lei. So that's why you have to say that's
why you have to say you have to be explicit in the
other case. אי נמי התם לא קאמר רבי התם אלא בחצר דלעלויי
רשותא בעי למשקל מיניה וכי יהיב ליה רשותא לעלויי תיב ונטר לך
קאמר ליה Ee nami hatam lo ka'amar Rebi hatam ela bechatzer d'le'iluyei
reshuta ba'ei lemishkal minei vechi yahiv lei reshuta le'iluyei tiv venatar lach
ka'amar lei and so there it's implicit. והכא הנח ואנא מנטרנא לך
קאמר ליה דאי סלקא דעתך הנח ותיב ונטר לך קאמר ליה אטו
טיבו רשותא בעי משקל מיניה? Vehacha hanach ve'ana menatarna lach ka'amar lei
de'ee salka daitach hanach vetiv venatar lach ka'amar lei atu tivu reshuta
ba'ei mishkal minei? Here because I don't need to give you any
permission to put it down saying put it down is also saying
I will guard it for you. Okay. The point I wanted to
make here was the ראשונים Rishonim which one do we follow? I
mean which one do we follow where's the
looks like we follow רבי. Rebi. We follow רבי. Rebi.
Which means they both say they both say in a way if
okay put your thing in my backyard so the implication is I'll
take responsibility because it's guarded. Yeah. And if it's in the שוק
shuk and I say put it down also the implication is that
I'm going to guard it because I don't need to give you
permission to put it down. Right. So in both those two cases
both in the חצר המשתמרת chatzer hamishtameret and also in the שוק
shuk there's an assumption that I'm assuming responsibility for the thing if
I say simply put it down. Yeah. Okay let's stop here.